Today's דף daf. *Daf* is כ"ט *Kaf Tet*. We're going to start
with the בבלי *Bavli*, time permitting we'll go back and do the
ירושלמי *Yerushalmi*, but we have to get through this discussion here about
relatives, which is a little complicated, and we basically saw that the
relatives who are פסול pasul *Posul* sort of extend to uncles and
cousins, only first cousins, not first cousins once removed, which would be
a שני בשלישי *Shaini be'Shlishi* or second cousins שלישי בשלישי *Shlishi be'Shlishi*
for those who remember the nomenclature, but it extends to cousins and
that's even through marriage, and the גמרא Gemara *Gmara* here had a
couple of ways of looking at the through marriage issue, whether it
starts with your like, mother-in-law or whether it ends with like your
son-in-law or something of that nature. But anyway, those are the things
that we saw. So now, we pick up with, and then we
actually did with מחותנים *Mechutanes*, what their story would be, or a
betrothed wife. So we pick up on the sixth wide line on
כ"ח עמוד ב' *Kaf Chet Amud Bet*, חורגו לבדו *Chorgo levado*. The
only one, however, it doesn't go down to children, to sons or
sons-in-law or whatever when deals with a stepson. It's only the stepson,
not your stepson's son or your stepson's son-in-law. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara *Gmara* says like this, תנו רבנן Tanu Rabbanan. *Tanu Rabbanan*,
our rabbis taught, six lines down in the wide lines כ"ח עמוד
ב' *Kaf Chet Amud Bet*, חורגו לבדו *Chorgo levado*, only your stepson
himself, no later generations. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi *Rabbi Yosi* אומר *omer*
גיסו *Giso*, actually also, actually
brother-in-law. Brother-in-law also doesn't, or we'll see about the also, doesn't go
down generations, it's brother-in-law but not brother-in-law's son or stepson or son-in-law,
excuse me. Okay, ותניא אידך *u'tanya idach*, we have another ברייתא braita
*Braitah*, גיסו לבדו *Giso levado*, the son of the brother-in-law, it stops
with him, it doesn't go to the brother-in-law's son or son-in-law. רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* אומר *omer* חורגו *Chorgo*, no, the stepson.
So the obvious question here is one is saying stepson and one
is saying son-in-law,
excuse me,
brother-in-law. Did I say son-in-law before? Brother-in-law. And the question is, to
what degree are they adding to one another or excluding one another,
right? How much does the one who says stepson say it's, I
would agree with you also about about
brother-in-law or vice versa? Yes.
Is this the brother-in-law of the stepson?
No, no, no.
But why would it be his own brother-in-law? Because that's like his
sister's, right.
So meaning what we've had before is, you know, we had here's,
here's whatever this guy and his sister, okay, brother and sister,
and then this is, right, brother-in-law, okay. And actually רש"י Rashi *Rashi*
even has a case that גיסו *Giso* could even be that these
two women are sisters. Right, okay, married and married. Okay, brother-in-law. And
we assumed that it would go also to the brother-in-law's son. Okay,
which is, which is a, which is an אחיין *achyan*, right, a
nephew. A nephew through marriage. Okay, right. So normally we assume that
nephews are included. But here we have a ברייתא Braitah, *Braitah* exactly
that has רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi *Rabbi Yosi* having who is it,
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi. *Rabbi Yosi* saying no, it's when you're dealing
with brother-in-law, it does not go down a generation.
And we're sure it's not the in-law of the stepson?
No, correct, correct.
No, no, no, no. He's saying you, תנא קמא *Tanna Kamma* or
it's whoever it is, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* say the
stepson doesn't go down in generation, I say the brother-in-law doesn't go
down in generation. Let's see where the גמרא Gemara *Gmara* goes, okay,
it's going to be clear.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gmara* says מאי קאמר *mai ka'amar*. Now,
the question is, what exactly is the debate? How much are what
they're saying complementing one another or excluding one another? So אילימא הכי
קאמר *ee'leima hachi ka'amar* חורגו לבדו *Chorgo levado* והוא הדין לגיסו *ve'hu
hadin le'Giso*, that the תנא קמא *Tanna Kamma* says it stops at
the stepson and it also stops at the brother-in-law, it doesn't go
down a generation. ואתא רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi למימר גיסו לבדו *ve'ata
Rabbi Yosi lemeimar Giso levado* והוא הדין לחורגו *ve'hu hadin le'Chorgo*. Not,
and רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi. *Rabbi Yosi* is saying it stops at
the brother-in-law and it also stops at the stepson. So then they're
both saying the same thing. They're just complementing one another and they're
both saying that stepson and brother-in-law doesn't go down a generation.
But משנתינו *mishnaseinu* דקתני *de'katni* גיסו הוא ובנו וחתנו *Giso hu u'veno
ve'chasno*, but our משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* says that a brother-in-law, it does
go down a generation, the brother-in-law's son and son-in-law, right, which would
be like the nephew through marriage. So מני *mani*, who's that go
like? לא רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda ולא רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi *lo
Rabbi Yehuda ve'lo Rabbi Yosi*, neither of them, because if you have
them complementing one another, then they're both agreeing that both stepson and
and excuse me, that both brother-in-law and stepson
don't go down a generation. But our משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* has brother-in-law
does go down a generation. So אלא הכי
קאמר *ella hachi ka'amar*, so here's how you have to read it.
חורגו לבדו *Chorgo levado*, that the רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda*
and who would be our משנה Mishnah, *Mishnah* should say stepson because
it's only stepson, there it doesn't go down a generation. חורגו לבדו
*chargo levado*. אבל גיסו *aval giso*, but when you deal with brother-in-law,
הוא בנו וחתנו *hu bino vechosno*, then it includes his son and
his son-in-law and so on, which is your nephew by marriage and
that's our משנה Mishnah *mishnah*. The only one who doesn't go down
a generation is stepson. Okay, so that's רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi
Yehudah*. ואתא רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi למימר *ve'asa Rabbi Yosi lemeimar* now
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi *Rabbi Yosi* says: No, גיסו לבדו *giso levado*
even when it comes to brother-in-law, excuse me,
brother-in-law doesn't go down a generation. אבל חורגו *aval chargo* but when
it comes to stepson הוא בנו וחתנו *hu bino vechosno* meaning that
they're mutually exclusive. Rather than complementing one another, they're debating. Each one
agrees that there's only one person in this list that it doesn't
go down a generation. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda, *Rabbi Yehudah* says it's
the stepson who doesn't go down a generation and that's our משנה
Mishnah *mishnah*. And רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi's *Rabbi Yosi* says it's the
brother-in-law that doesn't go down a generation, but the stepson would go
down a generation. Okay, so they're completely mutually exclusive. If that's true,
so where were... אבל גיסו הוא בנו וחתנו *aval giso hu bino
vechosno*. ואתא רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi למימר *ve'asa Rabbi Yosi lemeimar*... where
were we? אבל חורגו הוא בנו וחתנו *aval chargo hu bino vechosno*.
ואלא פשיטא *ve'ela peshita* so one of them would say it's only
the stepson that doesn't go down a generation, and the other would
say it's only the brother-in-law that doesn't go down a generation. ואלא
הא דתני רבי חייא *ve'ela ha detani Rabbi Chiyya* but okay, but
רבי חייא *Rabbi Chiyya* taught: שמונה אבות שהן עשרים וארבע *shmonah avos
shehen esrim ve'arba*. He said there are eight of these relatives, and
but once you extend it to their sons and stepsons, so that's
times you know that becomes twenty-four. They, their sons and their stepsons,
so eight becomes twenty-four. Alright, so כמאן *keman*? Now who's that going
like? לא כרבי יוסי ולא כרבי יהודה K'Rabbi Yehuda? *lo keRabbi Yosi
velo keRabbi Yehudah* it can't be either. Why? Because if you go
back and count the משנה Mishnah *mishnah*, the משנה Mishnah *mishnah* even
when you take off the stepson has nine relatives mentioned. I'm not
going to count it, you can go back and count it. Okay,
so the only way you're going to get to רבי חייא *Rabbi
Chiyya*'s teaching there's eight and eight becomes twenty-four, right? Is if you
say that there are two people that are not in the list.
And those two people not to be in the list would be
stepson and brother-in-law. Once you move stepson and brother-in-law, you would be
left with eight for whom you would include second generation. Okay, so
you got it. רבי חייא *Rabbi Chiyya* basically says our משנה Mishnah
*mishnah* has ten people listed. Okay, but רבי חייא *Rabbi Chiyya* says
of those ten, only eight of them you include their sons and
stepsons and it becomes twenty-four. So you have to eliminate two. So
which two are you going to eliminate? The only two that are
candidates to eliminate right now are stepson and brother-in-law. So it has
to be that there's a תנא *tanna* that says, that says both
of those are eliminated. So that's therefore going to lead us to
this way of understanding the debate. Okay. אלא הכי קאמר *ela hachi
ka'amar*. לא כמאן, לא כרבי יוסי ולא כרבי יהודה *lo keman, lo
keRabbi Yosi velo keRabbi Yehudah*. הכי קאמר *hachi ka'amar*. Here's how I
have to read it. חורגו לבדו *chargo levado*. That's the first opinion,
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehudah*, which is the author of our
משנה Mishnah *mishnah*, says stepson is the one which it doesn't go
down a generation. אבל גיסו הוא בנו וחתנו *aval giso hu bino
vechosno* it would go down a generation, that would be your nephew
through marriage. That's the author of the משנה Mishna *mishnah*, that's רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda. *Rabbi Yehudah*. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda, *Rabbi Yehudah* says
only stepson is the only one it doesn't go down a generation.
Why would it be like רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*?
ואתא רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi למימר *ve'asa Rabbi Yosi lemeimar* now רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yossi *Rabbi Yosi* comes and says: גיסו לבדו *giso levado*
included in your list in addition to the idea that the stepson
doesn't go down a generation, the brother-in-law doesn't go down a generation.
So I'm adding to your case of stepson that you're taking him
off the list of those that go down a generation and I'm
also putting on those who doesn't go down a generation, the brother-in-law,
the brother-in-law. Okay. וכל שכן חורגו *vechol shekein chargo* and certainly, if
brother-in-law doesn't go down a generation, brother-in-law seen as closer to you,
right, than the case of stepson. So if your brother-in-law doesn't go
down a generation, certainly your stepson. Okay, and now it all works
out. מתניתין רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *matnisin Rabbi Yehudah* our משנה Mishna,
*mishnah*'s רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda. *Rabbi Yehudah*. The only one our משנה
Mishna? *mishnah* takes off the list is stepson. Okay, and that's why
that's the only one that's not in the list of our משנה
Mishna, *mishnah* that goes down a generation. וברייתא *ubraisa* the ברייתא Braitah.
*braisa* of רבי חייא *Rabbi Chiyya* that says that there's only eight
who it would go down a generation and takes two people off
the list, who are the two that are being taken off the
list? I mean, who is that? That's רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi *Rabbi
Yosi*. That's רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi *Rabbi Yosi* because רבי יוסי Reb
Yosi *Rabbi Yosi* takes off the list both stepson and brother-in-law. Okay,
so you've got this case of brother-in-law and you've got this case
of okay,
stepson or somebody this woman has through a different, right, through a
different marriage. That's stepson.
That's stepson. That's חורגו *chargo*. And this is here גיסו *giso*. Okay,
so our משנה Mishna. *mishnah* said this guy is the only one
it doesn't go down a generation. Everybody else it does. So according
to our משנה Mishna, *mishnah* in this case, a nephew through marriage
would be, would be פסול pasul. *pasul*. Also not only that, even
like a cousin through marriage, right, would be פסול pasul *pasul*. Okay,
it does go down a, it does go down a generation. רבי
חייא *Rabbi Chiyya*... only eight people who it goes down a generation,
and according to our משנה Mishna there are nine, says this guy
it doesn't go down a generation and this guy it doesn't go
down a generation. And therefore you're left with eight people in our
משנה Mishna; who it does go down a generation. And this is
the position of רבי יוסי Reb Yosi, that says excluded from those
who it goes down a generation is both stepson and brother-in-law. Yes.
Can I ask something completely basic? Yes. Is the משנה Mishna. of
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva who we're trying to figure out who it
goes by?
Well,
within רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, there's a debate, I mean, it's a
good point, but within רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva you often have, you
know, there's a debate about the, the משנת רבי עקיבא Mishnat Rabbi
Akiva is the idea that you're not limited by ראוי לירשו. rauy
leyirsho. Okay? The משנה ראשונה Mishnah Rishonah was that you were, it
was limited to those who was ראוי לירשו rauy leyirsho and limited
to father's family and not mother's family and so on. רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva extended it. Within רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva who drops the
issue of ראוי לירשו, rauy leyirsho, okay, becomes now this debate of
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda. and רבי יוסי Reb Yosi
about when, you know, for which of these does it go down
a generation and for which does it not. So it's a debate
within משנת רבי עקיבא. Mishnat Rabbi Akiva. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara says like this, but good question.
Okay.
אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל הלכה כרבי יוסי. Amar Rav Yehuda Amar
Shmuel Halacha KeRabbi Yossi. We rule like רבי יוסי. Reb Yosi Okay,
so that's interesting. So now we're limiting the פסולים. psulim. It does,
it does not go down a generation not only for stepson, but
even for brother-in-law. Okay? So for even for brother-in-law it does not
go down a generation.
ההיא מתנתא. Hahi matanta. Now finally a story to break all of
these charts.
ההיא מתנתא, Hahi matanta, there was a gift דהוה חתים עליה תרי
גיסא. dehavei chatim alei terei gisei. Now the gift was mean a
שטר, shtar, somebody wrote out that he's giving, granting land to somebody
and the witnesses signed it and he hands over the שטר. shtar.
So the קנין kinyan that effected the transfer was the שטר. shtar.
So if there were פסול pasul. witnesses on the שטר, shtar, the
person never took possession of the land. It's not just a question
of proving it, right, you needed it to be a good שטר
shtar for the transfer to occur. And signed on that שטר shtar
were two brothers-in-law. These two guys were signed on the שטר. shtar.
Okay?
So now, now wait a minute. No, that doesn't work. One minute.
Because brothers-in-law are clearly פסול. posul? Hold on one minute, let me
just check it.
Oh, right, right, right, right. This is the issue. Okay, so now
we said that there's the רבי יוסי Reb Yosi of this ברייתא
that says by the brother-in-law it does not go down a generation.
So that was one thing we could have meant when we said
הלכה כרבי יוסי, Halacha KeRabbi Yossi, that by brother-in-law it does not
go down a generation. But if you turn back to the משנה,
Mishna? there's another, this is what Michael was reminding us of, there's
another statement of רבי יוסי. Reb Yosi And רבי יוסי Reb Yosi,
said זו משנת רבי עקיבא אבל משנה ראשונה zu mishnat Rabbi Akiva
aval Mishnah Rishonah said only somebody who's ראוי לירשו. rauy leyirsho. So
that might now, רבי יוסי Reb Yosi. might be telling us a
little historical fact that an earlier teaching was you only had to
be, it only was through the father's family and you had to
be in the line of inheritance. But he might actually be disagreeing
and the רבי יוסי Reb Yosi of the משנה Mishna might actually
be saying the only people who are פסול posul are people who
are in the line of inheritance. So according to that would brother,
forget the son of the brother-in-law, would brothers-in-law be כשר? kasher? Yes,
because they're not in the line of inheritance. They can't inherit from
one another. They're not going to pass property on through their wives.
If this guy dies, it doesn't go to his wife, right, wife's
property goes to the husband. There's no way that they're going to
manage to pass property on to one another. They're not in the
line of inheritance. So according to רבי יוסי's Reb Yosi teaching in
the משנה Mishna, of that the משנה ראשונה Mishnah Rishonah was you
had to be in a line of inheritance, forget even the kid,
brothers-in-law themselves would be כשר kasher to testify. So the question is
going to be when we said here in the name of שמואל,
Shmuel, הלכה כרבי יוסי, Halacha KeRabbi Yossi, which רבי יוסי Reb Yosi
did we mean? Did we mean רבי יוסי Reb Yosi, that says
children of brothers-in-law are okay, or do we mean רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yose in the משנה Mishna that says was much more radical, says
an earlier teaching was you had to be in a line of
inheritance, so even brothers-in-law themselves would be okay. So this was now
the case.
Do they inherit from each other? Because I mean, they can still
if there's two sisters and like let's say that there's a father?
No, that doesn't matter. It doesn't matter if it's going to go
like this. I can still testify against this guy because I'm never
going to, I'll never benefit from him. Right? Okay. So, all right,
so now he says so that's the case. So now we had
a שטר shtar with two brothers-in-law. סבר רב יוסף לאכשורה. Savar Rav
Yosef leachshura. רב יוסף Rav Yosef wanted to say the שטר shtar
was כשר. kasher. דאמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל הלכה כרבי יוסי. Deamar
Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel Halacha KeRabbi Yossi. And he thought it meant
רבי יוסי in the משנה Mishnah, and you go by the earlier
teaching pre-רבי עקיבא pre-Rabbi Akiva that you have to be in a
line of inheritance, which radically limits the scope of who's פסול. posul
אמר ליה אביי, Amar lei Abaye, אביי Abaye said to him ממאי
דרבי יוסי דמתניתין דמכשר בגיסי. mimai deRabbi Yossi dematnitin demachshar begisei. What
made you think that we're פוסק posek like רבי יוסי in our
משנה Mishna that goes by the משנה that predated רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva that would say brothers-in-law themselves are
כשר? kasher? No, no, no, we mean רבי יוסי of the ברייתא,
פסול בגיסיה. posul b'gise. He says a brother-in-law is no good. He
says a child of a brother-in-law would be okay. We don't go
to the kids of the brother-in-law, but brother-in-laws themselves are no good.
Okay, we פוסק posken like the משנה of רבי עקיבא. Rebbi Akiva.
So the גמרא Gemara says no, לא סלקא דעתך, lo salka daitach,
no, that didn't make sense to think that, דאמר שמואל, d'amar Shmuel,
because to think
that when שמואל Shmuel was פוסק poskening like רבי יוסי, he meant
רבי יוסי of the ברייתא. It makes sense that שמואל Shmuel was
פוסק poskening like רבי יוסי of the משנה, that brother-in-laws are actually
כשר, kosher, okay, if you're not in the line of inheritance. What
makes me think that's what שמואל's Shmuel פוסק? poskening? דאמר שמואל, d'amar
Shmuel, because שמואל Shmuel said, what's an example of the brother-in-law that's
פסול? posul. כגון אנא ופנחס, k'gon ana u-Pinchas, like me and פנחס,
Pinchas, דהוינאן אחי וגיסי. d'havinan achi v'gise. שמואל Shmuel said, what's an
example of a brother-in-law in the משנה? Like me and פנחס. Pinchas.
Now פנחס, Pinchas, if this would be here שמואל, Shmuel,
שמואל Shmuel had a brother, his name was
פנחס. Pinchas. Okay, yes, no, he had a brother whose name was
פנחס, Pinchas, and they happened to be married, the two brothers were
married to two sisters. Okay, so they were brothers and brothers-in-law. So
when שמואל Shmuel says, oh, שמואל Shmuel is thinking, let me give
you an example of a brother-in-law, like me and פנחס, Pinchas, we're
brother-in-laws. So now that's a very confusing example, okay, it could mean
had we not been brothers, this would be an example of the
brother-in-laws of the משנה, or what he could be saying is brother-in-laws
are really okay, the only brother-in-laws who would be פסול posul, would
be me and פנחס Pinchas because anyway we're brothers. Okay, so that's
how that was being read, that when שמואל Shmuel gave the example
that he and פנחס Pinchas are פסול pasul. as brother-in-laws, what he's
really teaching is brother-in-laws are okay, only brothers are no good. All
right, and that seems to be like the רבי יוסי of the
משנה. כגון אנא ופנחס דהוינאן אחי וגיסי. k'gon ana u-Pinchas d'havinan achi
v'gise. Okay, that's the גמרא's Gemara. read of what שמואל Shmuel means.
אבל גיסי דעלמא, aval gise d'alma, but presumably what שמואל Shmuel is
telling us is that normal brother-in-laws שפיר דמי shappir dami would be
okay, so it sounds like שמואל Shmuel is פוסק poskening that you
have to be in a line of inheritance. So the גמרא Gemara
says maybe not, ודילמא כגון אנא ופנחס משום דגיסא קאמר. u-dilma k'gon
ana u-Pinchas mishum d'gisa ka'amar. No, no, no, he meant an example
of brother-in-laws would be me and פנחס, Pinchas, bracketing the fact that
we're brothers, we would be an example of brother-in-laws. I don't know,
but אמר ליה, amar lei, it's like, you know, it just makes
it clear, I don't have any idea.
Okay, so anyway, so maybe we still פוסק posken like, not like
רבי יוסי of the משנה, that brother-in-laws are פסול. pasul. So אמר
ליה, amar lei, so this was the, what was the case here?
This case came in front of who? רב יוסף. Rav Yosef.
Okay, so
רב יוסף Rav Yosef said,
so אביי Abaye was giving רב יוסף Rav Yosef a hard time,
which אביי Abaye often does. Okay, so רב יוסף Rav Yosef said
fine, maybe the שטר shtar is פסול, pasul but we'll get you
to take possession of the land the following way. אמר ליה, amar
lei, he said to the person who came before him to דין,
din, זיל קני ביהדי מסירה. zil kanyi b'eidei mesira. Fine, so maybe
the witnesses on the שטר shtar are no good, they were brother-in-laws,
maybe אביי Abaye is right, maybe brother-in-laws are no good, but you
know what? There were witnesses that saw the שטר shtar being handed
over. And we can say that if there are witnesses that see
it, the witnesses become like they're part of the שטר. shtar. That's
עדי מסירה כרתי, eidei mesira karthi, witnesses that see it handed over
become part of the שטר. shtar. So even if the שטר shtar
didn't work because of the brother-in-laws who were signed on it, let
it work because of the עדי מסירה eidei mesira to רבי אלעזר,
Reb Elazar, like רבי אלעזר Reb Elazar that says that עדי מסירה
eidei mesira are effective. So the גמרא Gemara says, אביי Abaye presumably
or somebody said, no, you can't do that, והא אמר רבי אבא
מודה רבי אלעזר במזויף מתוכו שהוא פסול. v'ha amar Rabbi Abba Modeh
Reb Elazar bimzuyaph mitocho shehu posul. Even רבי אלעזר Reb Elazar says
you go by the עדי מסירה, eidei mesira, that's only if the
שטר shtar itself is okay. But if the שטר shtar itself has
something that makes it invalid, if there are bad witnesses in the
שטר, shtar, the good witnesses outside of the שטר shtar can't come
and erase the bad witnesses in the שטר. shtar. מזויף מתוכו?
mizuyaph mitocho? Not that there's an actual problem with the שטר shtar
in terms of like,
no, מזויף מתוכו mizuyaph mitocho is a broader point. It doesn't just
mean a forgery or a crossed out, it means something is intrinsically
problematic in the שטר. shtar. So if there's no witnesses, the עדים
eidim outside can be the witnesses, but if there's bad witnesses, the
עדים eidim outside the שטר shtar cannot make it into a good
שטר. shtar. אמר ליה, amar lei, so רב יוסף Rav Yosef said
to this person who came before him,
I'm sorry buddy, you gotta go, לא שבקי לי דאזבין לך. lo
shavki li d'ezbin lach.
They're not letting me award you the field. אביי Abaye is giving
me a hard time basically, he's פוסל posuling the witnesses, he's telling
me I can't use עדי מסירה, eidei mesira, I'm sorry, okay, you
lost your case. Okay, but the גמרא Gemara, never comes out conclusively,
right? שמואל Shmuel said like רבי יוסי, that we were like רבי
יוסי. Which רבי יוסי did it mean? Did it mean רבי יוסי
who says you don't go to the child of a brother-in-law? Or
did it mean the רבי יוסי who says no, it has to
be, we go like the early teaching, only if you're in a
line of inheritance? The פסק psak is like רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva
in the משנה and not like רבי יוסי, okay, that it is
the much broader scope. You do not have to be in the
line of inheritance. It goes to, like I said, cousins, you know,
שני בשני sheini b'sheini and so on, okay, and it does. And
it goes through wives and through mothers and so on, and it
is not limited to cases of in the line of inheritance. Okay,
so we do not rule like רבי יוסי of the משנה; we
actually rule like רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva of the משנה. Yes.
I'm so surprised, you know, with רב אבא בר יוסף בר ארסן
אקני, Rav Abba bar Yosef bar Arsan Akni, I can't imagine any
תלמיד חכם talmid chacham getting your Exactly, Michael.
Okay, רבי יהודה אומר. Rabbi Yehuda Omer. Now, we're finally about getting
ready to turn the bend here on this very challenging דף. Now,
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda, said, okay, who was רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda.
of the משנה? רבי יהודה said,
oh, the last case of the relative, what happens if you were
a קרוב ונתרחק? karov v'nitrachak? How could you have been a relative
and then stopped being a relative? If you were a relative through
marriage, okay? So what, so
and then you became distant because the woman that was, you know,
that made the through marriage between these two men, the woman died.
Okay, or divorced. Okay, so,
but רבי יהודה says it depends if you have surviving kids. Okay?
If this man's daughter
is married to this guy, okay, so he's the son-in-law,
okay? So that would be a classic case about a קרוב karov
through marriage, and then she dies. Okay, so then it's just my,
then it's this guy's, like, you know, this guy's
daughter who passed away, her her ex-husband, so no relationship anymore, so
he's כשר. kasher. But says רבי יהודה, if there are kids,
okay, then this guy is not just his ex-son-in-law, this guy is
the father of his grandkids. And if this guy is the father
of his grandkids, he remains פסול. pasul That's what רבי יהודה says.
Okay, so if there are surviving kids, he would be פסול. pasul?
Okay, so let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara אמר רבי תנחום אמר רב טבלא אמר רב ברונא אמר
רב, Amar Rabbi Tanchum amar Rav Tavla amar Rav Bruna amar Rav,
הלכה כרבי יהודה. halacha k'Rabbi Yehuda. We rule like רבי יהודה. רבא
אמר רב נחמן אין הלכה כרבי יהודה. Rava amar Rav Nachman ein
halacha k'Rabbi Yehuda. We don't rule like him. וכן אמר רבה בר
בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן אין הלכה כרבי יהודה. V'chen amar Rabba
bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan ein halacha k'Rabbi Yehuda. We don't
rule like him. איכא דמתני להא דרבה בר בר חנה אהא. Ika
d'masni l'ha d'Rabba bar bar Chana a'ha.
Some teach this teaching of רבה בר בר חנה Rabba bar bar
Chana on the following statement. הזוהי דרש רבי יוסי הגלילי. H'zohee darash
Rabbi Yose HaGlili. This is what רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGlili
teaches. ובאת אל הכהנים הלוים ואל השופט אשר יהיה בימים ההם. U'bas
el h'Kohanim h'Levi'im v'el h'Shofet asher yi'hyeh b'yamim h'hem. You shall come
to the judge that will be in those times. וכי תעלה על
דעתך שאדם הולך אצל שופט שלא היה בימיו? V'chi sa'aleh al da'at'cha
she'adam holech eitzel shofet she'lo hayah b'yamav? What are you gonna do?
Get in a time machine? You're gonna go to a judge who's
not gonna be at those times? What do you mean go to
a judge who will be at those times? So normally that דרשה
drasha ends by talking about the authority of the judges of every
generation, that each generation, you know, you go by your authorities and
you don't think and you don't sort of discount them because they're
not as great as previous generations. But here it's a different דרשה.
drasha. אלא זה שהיה קרוב ונתרחק. Ella zeh she'hayah karov v'nitrachak.
He means if now he can be a judge for you because
now you're not related to him, okay, even though before he couldn't
be a judge to you because before you were related to him
through marriage. But בימים ההם, b'yamim h'hem, if at the time when
you have your judgment he's a legitimate judge, then you can go
to him even though he was related to you before. And on
this teaching, אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן הלכה כרבי
יוסי הגלילי. amar Rabba bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan halacha k'Rabbi
Yose HaGlili. We rule like רבי יוסי הגלילי. Rabbi Yose HaGlili. Now,
that's not saying anything too much new, that's just the general teaching
that if you were קרוב ונתרחק, karov v'nitrachak, you're כשר. kasher. That's
not getting into the question about what if there are surviving kids.
Okay, so now we're gonna have a story. בני חמוה דמר עוקבא,
B'nei chamu'eh d'Mar Ukva, the sons of the mother-in-law of מר עוקבא.
Mar Ukva. Okay,
so who are the sons of his mother-in-law? Okay, if this is
מר עוקבא, Mar Ukva,
okay,
so the sons of his mother-in-law, here's his mother-in-law,
the sons of his mother-in-law are his wife's brothers.
His brothers-in-law. Okay,
so his brothers-in-law. Okay,
so he's related through marriage. Okay, so בני חמוה דמר עוקבא, b'nei
chamu'eh d'Mar Ukva, קרובים ונתרחקו הוו. krovim v'nitrachku havu. They were קרובים
ונתרחקו. krovim v'nitrachku. How will that happen? What happened? Sadly his wife
passed away.
So now they're just his, right, his ex-brother-in-law, except it's with rather
than father-in-law, it's with brother-in-law. They're his ex-brothers-in-law. Okay, but he's gonna
have, he well, he has kids. Now, this is a little bit
different. This is not somebody, it's not like going up here and
it's the, you know, and it's my, you know, it's my kids'
grandfather. This is here just brothers, it's my kids' uncle. Okay, they're
not related to me at all, but they're my kids' uncle. Does
that make them, does that make them פסולים psulim to me? All
right, so אתו לקמיה לדינא. atu l'kamei l'dina. So, so they came
in front of him for a דין. din. So now we're dealing
with a case of the these brothers, these guys came for a
דין din before him because remember we just mentioned השופט אשר יהיה
בימים ההם h'Shofet asher yi'hyeh b'yamim h'hem which extends the פסולים psulim
of קרובים krovim extends not... not only to עדים edim but to
דיינים. dayanim. Well, that's what we've been assuming all along that a
קרוב karov is also פסול pasul. as a דיין. dayan. So here
the case was, they came before him as a דין. din. Is
he good to be a דיין dayan for them? They were his
ex-brothers-in-law so that they could be—they could be כשר, kasher, but according
to רבי יהודה, they're still his uncles, they're still uncles of his
kids. Okay. So אתו לקמיה לדינא. Atu kamei l'dina. אמר להו, Amar
lehu, he said to them, פסילנא לכו לדינא. Psilna l'chu l'dina. I'm
פסול pasul to be a דיין dayan for you. אמרו ליה, Amru
lei, they said to him, מאי דעתך? Mai daitach? כרבי יהודה? Do
you think we're going like רבי יהודה that just because we're your
kids' uncles, we should be פסול? pasul? אנן, Anan, מייתינא איגרתא ממערבא,
maitina igarta mi'Maarava, we'll get a letter from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
דאין הלכה כרבי יהודה, d'ein halacha k'Rabbi Yehuda, that we don't rule
like רבי יהודה. And even though the kids are still we're still
your kids' uncles, we're no longer related to you and you should
be כשר kasher to judge for us. אמר להו, Amar lehu, he
said back to them, אטו בכפתא דדקולא אידבקנא בכו? Atu b'kafta d'dikula
idbakna b'chu? What, do you think I am stuck to you like
a like a like with a pound of wax? Meaning it's not
because we're related. Okay, it's a great phrase. Right. You think we're
like we're stuck together with glue? You think that's the problem? Tied
together with—right.
You think that's the problem? The problem isn't that we're related. Fine,
we don't פסקן pasken like רבי יהודה. Fine, we're not related. That's
not why I don't want to be your judge. So לא קאמינא
פסילנא לכו לדינא, lo kamina psilna l'chu l'dina, אלא משום דלא צייתיתו
לדינא. ela mishum d'la tzyyitu l'dina. I only said that I'm invalid
to be a judge not because we're related, but because you guys
are troublemakers and you won't listen. So this really means I'm recusing
myself, it doesn't really mean I'm פסול. pasul. I don't want to
be your judge because you are you refuse to listen to the
פסקים. psakim. Okay, which you can see already that they're starting to,
"Oh, maybe he just—maybe we rule like רבי יהודה, right? We rule
against רבי יהודה." They're already, you see, troublemakers. "We're going to go
to ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. We're going to get a letter." So
you know what? Go—go to somebody else to be your judge. Okay.
So fine, it ends with that. So we don't know—we don't know
how he פסקן. pasken. Okay. But we are finally now out of
the discussion of relatives. All right. Now the end of the משנה
talked about somebody who is a—who's a very close person, a very
close friend, אוהב, ohev, that's פסול psul. to be an עד. ed.
So what does that mean? How close of a friend? Okay, so
it said אחד השושבינים, echad ha'shoshvinim, one of the people that were
the that were like at—in the wedding party, the groomsman, very, very
close. Yeah, let me just read this. And then the גמרא Gemara
qualifies that, וכמה, v'chama, and how long are you פסול? psul So
אמר רבי אבא אמר רבי ירמיה אמר רב, Amar Rabbi Abba amar
Rabbi Yirmiyah amar Rav, כל שבעת ימי המשתה, kol shivat yemei ha'mishteh,
for the entire week of the wedding. But after that, just because
you were my groomsman at my wedding doesn't mean afterwards you'll be
פסול. psul. During that week, we're feeling all very, very tight and
chummy and close. That's when you can't be an עד. ed. רבנן
משמיה דרבא אמרי אפילו מיום ראשון ואילך. Rabanan mishmei d'Rava amri afilu
mi'yom rishon v'eilach. You know what? Even the first day after the
wedding, they're already כשר. kasher. That the concern that because—meaning they don't
believe—it sort of goes like that line in the משנה, לא נחשדו
ישראל על כך, lo nechshedu Yisrael al kach, okay, which is basically
a point that like it's one thing that the תורה Torah formally
excludes relatives. Yes, the logic behind relatives is that you'll be inclined
to—you'll be influenced because of your relationship with them. And the גמרא
Gemara used it to say that it applies even to a betrothed
wife and not a married wife. But all that being said, at
least that's a formal פסול. psul To just start now excluding people
because they're friends or enemies or whatever, we want to really limit
that. Okay. And therefore we, A, it's hard to measure, and B,
it's like we—we would like to not assume that people are going
to testify falsely as a result of this. So therefore we're going
to limit the case in the משנה to just the day of
the wedding itself. Now what we're going to see though is, is
that that's when it comes to being an עד. ed. When it
comes to being a דיין, dayan, we do have a broader category
of an אוהב ohev and a שונא. sonei. And the logic being
that if I'm a witness, to think that because I'm good pals
here with Michael, I'm going to testify falsely means that it's going
to cloud my objectivity consciously or unconsciously of just reporting the facts
that I saw. So that would have to be like I'm just
reporting the facts that I
saw. So there they would have to usually be like
we don't want to assume that—not consciously I'm going to misrepresent them,
but maybe even in a subconscious, that's sort of one degree. But
to be a judge, a judge isn't just like just reporting what
you saw. A judge is starting to say, "Wait, wait, but maybe
this and maybe that and let's think and argue on somebody's behalf
and argue both sides." And there it's much more likely that if
you have feelings for or against someone, you're not going to be
pushing as much to argue on that person's behalf or the—or pushing
as much to argue against that person. So that's a type of
a case where we need more freedom from any types of
influences.
Yes. Question on these—this discussion. Just because somebody's no longer related officially
because somebody passes away, why would they think that the feelings and
considerations—right,
so that's a good question and it ties into this
issue. It's not—so that's the point, that by
relatives, feelings might be there, but then we would assess it through
the אוהב ohev and the שונא. sonei. The formal category of relative
stops applying once there's no longer a relationship. Whether there's still feelings,
you know, you somebody could have been my buddy from high school
for the last 30 years, right? And that would not be פסול
psul. because he wasn't a groomsman during my week of my wedding,
right? So that's what exactly what we're dealing with.
He should be פסול. psul. What? Best friend's guy, you shouldn't...
But that's no, but according to the משנה, even the category of
אוהב ohev is extremely narrowly drawn. As a judge, it's broader, but
that's the exact point. As a witness, which is basically just about
reporting accurately what you saw. Now, of course we all know, studies
have been done that, you know, that eyewitness testimony is grossly inaccurate.
Okay, you know, used to be the whole thing when they started
doing the science of forensics, right, courts didn't want to accept it
because nothing could be as good as somebody testifying to what they
directly saw, right? You know, and הלכה halacha also, like what you
directly saw, that's the ideal. Okay, but you know, we know that
actually that, you know, that, you know, they've done a lot of
studies. You know, somebody runs into a room, does something, runs out
and then they ask everybody there, what did you just see, right?
And it's grossly inaccurate. So anyway, I don't know what to say,
but the assumption here is, is that when it's about testifying to
what you saw, there's a formal פסול psul? of being a relative,
but once that's removed, we're not going to really worry about how
friendly or, you know, how close you are or how antagonistic you
are, except in very narrowly defined cases. Yes.
I think it's not about feelings, I think it's of like releasing
the ties between the people because the in-law, now no longer married
into this family, can marry into a different family. So I don't
think they're concerned with feelings. And the other thing I've mentioned before,
to my knowledge, there is no Hebrew word for objective and subjective.
אובייקטיבי. objektivi.
Right.
Exactly. Exactly.
So somehow that's not a concept that the תורה Torah sees at
all or possible.
Otherwise, yeah.
I mean, you can say ללא משוא פנים. le-lo maso panim. Right.
Right, right.
That's right, right, right. But you... Right,
meaning influenced, you're right. I mean, that's a lot, right? השם אלוקיכם
אשר לא ישא פנים ולא יקח שוחד. Hashem Elokeichem asher lo yisa
panim v'lo yikach shochad.
So being influenced, right, you know, and to show favor, but yeah,
that's an interesting point that you don't have the words objective and
subjective.
Now, you were going to say שונא. soneh. Is that the same
like הלכה halacha thing here?
Well, let's take a look. Oh, you... Well, okay, we can worry
about that by מכות, Makkot, but but let's take a look here.
Now, it is interesting, אוהב ohev is a very narrow category. Your
groomsman during the week of your wedding. שונא soneh is a little
bit broader. Somebody that you have not spoken to for three days
because you're in a fight, and as long as the two of
you are on the outs, you're פסול. So that could be a
much broader category, right, of people. So that actually is interesting, because,
you know, hate is a often is a more is a stronger
emotion than like love. You know, like they actually show that in
like, what is it, in like elections, you know, that there was
like a case about I don't know somebody it was like a
recall election and there were some people that were, you know, really,
really angry about this governor and they were sort of pushing, you
know, to recall him or whatever, and the guy got recalled. And
then they actually did a poll, like how many people wanted to
keep this governor in place, and it was like 70% wanted to
keep the guy in place. So why'd he get recalled? Because it
was only the other 30% who turned out to vote. You know,
the hate is a driver to people much more to like mobilize
and to turn out to vote than the fact that they're in
favor of something. So actually the category of שונא soneh actually is
broader. And
as long as they're not speaking to each other. As long as
they're, right, on the outs and haven't spoken to each other for
three... oh, for at least three days, then they're שונא soneh and
פסול עדות. psul edut. And exactly. השונא כל שלא דיבר. ha-soneh kol
she-lo diber. תנו רבנן. So now let's see what it's based on.
והוא לא אויב לו, v'hu lo oyev lo, so the פסוק pasuk
is ולא מבקש רעתו. v'lo mivakesh ra'ato. This is about the case
about the person who who killed by unintentionally and he goes to
the עיר מקלט. ir miklat. So it's sort of saying he didn't
intentionally kill, he wasn't an enemy, he wasn't lying in wait. But
we're not reading it as whether the the person who killed was
intentional or not, we're reading it as the person who's testifying about
him, he can testify to the fact that he killed. And the
reason he can testify to the fact that he killed was he's
not this guy's enemy. והוא
לא אויב לו, v'hu lo oyev lo, if he's not an enemy
to him, יעידנו, ye'idenu, then he can testify about what he did.
ולא מבקש רעתו, v'lo mivakesh ra'ato, he's not looking to do evil
to him, ידיננו, yadinenu, then he can be a דיין dayan if
he's not an enemy. אשכחן שונא. ashkechan soneh. So that's the category
that שונא soneh is פסול. אוהב מנלן? ohev minnalan? How do you
know an אוהב ohev is פסול? And as I just said, it
doesn't necessarily follow one from the other. So קרי ביה הכי. kari
bei hachi. Oh, we'll read it into the פסוק. pasuk. והוא לא
אויב לו, v'hu lo oyev lo, if you're not an enemy, ולא
אוהב, v'lo ohev, and if you're not a particularly close friend, then
יעידנו. ye'idenu. ולא מבקש רעתו, v'lo mivakesh ra'ato, you're not looking to
do bad to him, ולא טובתו, v'lo tovaso, and you're not looking
to do good to him, then ידיננו. yadinenu. So basically we just
read it in, we read it into the gap between the words,
okay? there's nothing in the פסוקים *Psukim* about that. So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says מידי אוהב כתיב *Midi Ohev Ktiv*? What are you
doing? It's not written there. There talks about hating, it doesn't talk
about loving. So אלא סברא הוא *Ella Sevara Hu*. It's a סברא
*Sevara*. אוהב מאי טעמא *Ohev Mai Ta'ama*? Why isn't אוהב *Ohev* not
a כשר עד *Kasher Ed* or דיין *Dayan*? דמרחקא דעתיה *Demarchaka Da'ateih*
that you feel very distant from the person? אוהב נמי מיקרבא דעתיה
*Ohev Nami Mikrava Da'ateih*. So the truth for it's in the reverse;
if you love this person, then you feel you're close to them
and that'll influence your testimony and your and your judging. So רבנן
*Rabbanan*. Now the רבנן *Rabbanan* would say so which is the רבנן
*Rabbanan*? Oh, so the רבנן *Rabbanan* of oh the רבנן *Rabbanan* who
said that לא נחשדו ישראל על כך *Lo Nechshadu Yisrael Al Kach*.
Okay the רבנן *Rabbanan* who said that we're not concerned that because
you're an אוהב *Ohev* or שונא *Sonei* that will ever influence your
testimony. You're always כשר *Kasher* to testify, not as a relative, but
as an אוהב *Ohev* and a שונא *Sonei*. What do they do
with this פסוק *Pasuk*? היי לא אויב לו ולא מבקש רעתו מאי
דרשי ביה *Hai Lo Oyev Lo Velo Mevakesh Ra'ato Mai Darshi Beih*?
What do they do with it? חד לדיין *Chad Ledayan* one for
a judge. If they say as a witness you're כשר *Kasher*, but
a judge אוהב *Ohev* and שונא *Sonei* is still פסול *Pasul*. That's
what I said. It's not just there about reporting what you saw;
it's about arguing both sides and trying to argue, you know, critique
side, defending side, that requires much, you know, much more disinterestedness, free
of feelings. Okay. And therefore for a דיין *Dayan* everybody agrees that's
a פסול *Psul*. אידך *Idach* the other פסוק *Pasuk* that's אוהב *Ohev*
and כדתניא *Kidtanya*. אמר רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה *Amar Rabbi Yossi Berabbi
Yehuda* והוא לא אויב לו ולא מבקש רעתו *Vehu Lo Oyev Lo
Velo Mevakesh Ra'ato* מכאן לשני תלמידי חכמים ששונאים זה את זה שאין
יושבים בדין כאחד *Mikan Lishnei Talmidei Chachamim Shesoneim Zeh Et Zeh She-ein
Yoshvin Badin Ke'echad*. The same way you can't have relatives who are
they you can't testify against a relative and you can't testify with
a relative, you can't be, right, you understand, you can't be with
him and you can't be against. Now you can't be together as
עדים *Edim* and you can't be against someone, you can't be a
judge for somebody you love or hate and you also can't be
be a judge together with somebody you hate. Presumably you could be
a judge together with somebody you love, okay? But you but you
understand the difference, right? If Michael and I are here all both
pals and we're in a and we're in בית דין Beit Din.
*Beit Din* together, the fact that we're pals isn't, you know, we
can be pals and disagree, right, and that's not going to influence
me critiquing, you know, the whole sort of model of Rabbinic debate,
right, the Rabbis give is like, you know, that when they sit
down to argue they're like enemies and then when they get up
and they're done with the חברותא *Chavruta*, you know, they're like, you
know, they're the best of friends. So the fact that we are
very close is not going to influence us being on the same
בית דין Beit Din *Beit Din* together. But if we really hate
one another, then I'm going to just to spite argue against what
he says and I'm not going to want to listen to him
and I'm not right it's going to influence the dynamics. It's not
going to be the proper type of open atmosphere that we need
to have to have a case of a דין *Din*. So שונאים
*Sonim* are פסול *Pasul* to be דיינים *Dayanim* together. אוהבים *Ohavim* are
not פסול *Pasul* to be דיינים *Dayanim* together. Moves on to that,
right? Right, yeah. Okay, so that is the case of the קרובים
*Krovim* and then the issue of שונא *Sonei* and אוהב *Ohev* which
could be a very big category. אוהב *Ohev* is limited and the
question also about how does it maybe shift between witnesses and judges.
Now we turn to the classic משנה *Mishnah* about the process of
examining the witnesses. כיצד בודקין את העדים *Keitzad Bodkin Et Ha-edim*? How
do you check the witnesses? Okay, and you all know the whole
משנה *Mishnah* about, you know, when they're coming for דיני נפשות Dinei
Nefashos. *Dinei Nefashot* you say, you know, you know all the future
generations, etc. This is not דיני נפשות *Dinei Nefashot*. This is דיני
ממונות Dinei mamonot. *Dinei Mamonot*. Okay? How do you check the witnesses
in let's say a civil case? So הכניסן לחדר *Hachnisan Lacheder* they
would bring them into a room, ומאיימין עליהם *Umaimin Aleihem* and you
would scare them. It doesn't say what you would say to scare
them, but by the דיני נפשות *Dinei Nefashot* we know a little
bit what you'd say to scare them. Here the משנה *Mishnah* doesn't
say. ומוציאין את כל האדם לחוץ *Umotzi'in Et Kol Ha-adam Lachutz*. You
take everybody out. Actually the גרסא *Girsa* in some משניות *Mishnayot* say
ומוציאין אותן לחוץ *Umotzi'in Otan Lachutz*. You take all the not everybody,
not like everybody who's gathered, but just the other witnesses out. And
you leave behind one of the witnesses and now you're going to
sort of examine each witness individually. Okay, but it doesn't mean you
clear the whole court, if you depending on your גרסא *Girsa*. Okay.
ומשיירין את הגדול שבהן *Umshayirin Et Hagadol Shebahen*. You leave the the
older witness, I don't know why specifically whether it means older, whether
it means more, you know, of a greater status. ואומרים לו *V'omrin
Lo* and you say to him: אמור היאך אתה יודע שזה חייב
chayav, לזה *Emor Heich Atah Yode'a Shezeh Chayav Lazeh*? How do you
know this person owes somebody a hundred dollars? You said he owed
him a hundred dollars. How do you know that exactly? אם אמר
הוא אמר לי שאני חייב לו *Im Amar Hu Amar Li She-ani
Chayav Lo*? Because, you know, Reuven said to me we were out
getting ice cream and Reuven said to me: You know, I owe
Shimon a hundred dollars. Okay. או איש פלוני אמר לי שהוא חייב
לו *O Ish Ploni Amar Li Shehu Chayav Lo* or, you know,
a friend told me that Reuven owed Shimon a hundred dollars. So
לא אמר כלום *Lo Amar Klum*. You didn't say anything. Now of
course the second case is pure hearsay, you understand why the second
case, but why is the first case not? Because the first case
is: We were just in conversation and he was saying: I owe
Shimon a hundred dollars. You know, that he didn't give it any
weight and sometimes you could say דווקא *Dafka* things you say in
passing be more believed, right? But we'll see in the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* that you know he could just have been סתם *Stam* talking
and there could be reasons why he'll say it even if it's
not true. So לא אמר כלום *Lo Amar Klum* he doesn't want
to seem overly rich or whatever. Right. So לא אמר כלום *Lo
Amar Klum*. So none of that is binding. עד שיאמר, that's the
only admission that is acceptable is, I mean obviously if they say
I saw him borrow the hundred dollars. But in case of admission,
the only admission that's acceptable is if he says בפנינו הודה לו
שחייב לו מאתיים זוז. Befaneinu hodeh lo shechayav lo matayim zuz. I
was there and I saw Shimon say to Reuven, yes I owe
you a hundred dollars. He admitted it not just to me when
we were out getting ice cream, he admitted it to the guy
who he says he owes the money to and I was there.
Okay, that's an admission. Now, ואחר כך מכניסין את השני ובודקין אותו.
Veachar kach machnisin et hasheni uvodkin oto. Then you excuse the first
one and you bring in the second one and you check him.
אם נמצאו דבריהם מכוונין, Im nimtzeu divreihem mechuvavin, if what they say
lines up, נושאים ונותנים בדבר. Nosnim venosnim badavar. Then you debate the
issue. שנים אומרים זכאי ואחד אומר חייב, Shnayim omrim zakai veechad omer
chayav, if two say innocent and one say guilty, זכאי, zakai, innocent.
שנים אומרים חייב ואחד אומר זכאי, Shnayim omrim chayav veechad omer zakai,
two say guilty one say innocent, חייב, he's guilty or if we're
not here dealing with monetary issues and not crime, you know, he
owes him the money. Okay. Now, אחד אומר חייב ואחד אומר זכאי.
Echad omer chayav veechad omer zakai. Now let's say one says he
owes him the money and one says he doesn't owe him the
money and the other guy just says I don't know. Or even
in a more extreme case, אפילו שנים מזכין, Afillu shnayim mezakin, two
people say he's exempt, או שנים מחייבין, O shnayim mechayvin, or two
say he owes the money, and the other guy wouldn't matter how
he would vote, you already have a majority. As long as אחד
אומר איני יודע, Echad omer eini yodea, as long as one guy
says I don't know, even if his vote doesn't matter, once he
says he doesn't know it's like he's no longer part of the
בית דין. Beit Din. And then you don't have a בית דין
Beis Din of three people. So יוסיפו הדיינים, Yosifu hadayanim, you have
to add judges. Of course the problem is you only add them
in pairs, so it might take a while, right? Because now you
have an even number of people on the בית דין. Okay. We'll
see the whole process. We need to keep on adding until you
get one that's going to be, you know. Well we'll see the
whole process. The whole process of adding judges will come up. He
doesn't know how to rule. Does he stay on that court? Right.
So we had that also a little bit before from an earlier
גמרא, Gemara it sounded like once he said he doesn't know he
can't vote again. But other גמרא sound a little different and תוספות
Tosafot tries to reconcile it. Okay, so those are discussions we'll have
later on. Now, גמר הדבר. Gamar hadavar. Now let's say they did
come to a conclusion. היו מכניסין אותן, Hayu machnisin otan, they would
bring back the litigants, for the debate was not in the presence
of the litigants. Okay. הגדול שבדיינים אומר, Hagadol shebadayanim omer, איש פלוני
אתה זכאי איש פלוני אתה חייב. Ish ploni atah zakai, ish ploni
atah chayav. So the elder of the judges issues the judgment: "So-and-so
you are exempt" or you know "you're innocent", "so-and-so you're liable" or
"you're guilty". ומנין שכשיצא לא יאמר, Uminayin shekesheyeitzei lo yomar, now how
do you know that after the case is over one of the
judges should not go over to the litigant and say, the guy
who was found guilty, אני מזכך, Ani mezakecha, "you know what you
should know I really found you innocent". Okay. וחברי מחייבין, Vachaverai mechayvin,
"but it was my other two colleagues, they outvoted me, they found
you guilty". אבל מה אעשה שחברי רבו עלי, Aval mah eseh shechaverai
ravu alai, "what could I do that my colleagues, they outvoted me".
How do you know you're not allowed to say that? על זה
נאמר, Al zeh neemar, לא תלך רכיל בעמך, Lo telech rachil beamecha,
"do not go as a talebearer". ואומר הולך רכיל מגלה סוד, Veomer
holech rachil megaleh sod, the one who's a talebearer goes and reveals
secrets. Now it's very interesting and we'll discuss this not today but
you know, but the way in nowadays, you know, when the Supreme
Court issues a ruling, you know, the minority, you know, they write
up their whole opinion. Here's why we were in the minority, here's
why we voted against it, here's was our reason. And
הלכה Halacha in general likes the idea of a דעת יחיד. Daat
yachid. You preserve minority opinions because you might want to go back
and rely on them at a later time. But there's a difference
between preserving it as a theoretical opinion, like to know that there
is this argument out there and there's an opinion that maybe a
later judge wants to rely on, as opposed to in a particular
case because you want the court to be ruling with the full
one voice of the court. Exactly. We as a court have decided
so-and-so. And also this whole type of a dynamic is going to
lead to trying to influence... it's going to get obviously you know
we discuss it later, but you could imagine, like very messy. You
know, it undermines the authority of the court, it makes people more
pick sides, it removes objectivity. You know, you start feeling bad for
the guy, "why am I telling Michael I voted for him? I
don't want him to be angry at me", right? So that opens
the court to more types of influence. Right. So anyway, you have
to sort of speak as a unified court.
One of us does the same thing with parenting.
Oh that's a good... that's an excellent analogy, right? It's like the
parents speaking in one voice. It's like, "yeah you know I really
think you could go out and get another ice cream but you
know Mom says you can't", right? That's a good point. That's a
good example. It's like you do not want everybody picking sides. You
want to speak in a unified voice. Okay, so היכי אמרינן להו?
Heichi amrinan lehu? So now the גמרא says okay we scare them.
How do we scare them? This is a דיני ממונות. Dinei Mamonos,
It's a... It's a good point. It's a good example. It's like
you do not want everybody picking sides. You want to speak in
a unified voice. Okay. So, היכי אמרינן להו? Heichi amrinan lehu? So
now the גמרא says, okay, we scare them. How do we scare
them? This is a דיני ממונות, it isn't a דיני נפשות. You
don't say somebody's life is in your hands. How do we scare
them? So אמר רב יהודה הכי אמרינן להו. Amar Rav Yehuda hachi
amrinan lehu. This is what we say to them: נשיאים ורוח וגשם
אין, Nesi'im veruach vegeshem ayin, you know clouds and winds and then
no rain, איש מתהלל במתת שקר, ish mithallel bematat shaker, so like
a person who praises himself with a false gift. So here you
are, you know, you're making all, you know, so if you are,
so you're coming and testifying, it's not exactly that, it's sort of
like somebody who makes a promise and doesn't keep it, but you're
testifying falsely, it's like the clouds are false testimony that there's going
to be rain and they don't bring the rain. So what? So
it's being read as, as a result of your false testifying, there
will be no rain. So the גמרא says, אמר רבא, Amar Rava,
so רבא Rava said, יכיל למימר, yachil lemeimar, so he could say,
big deal, I'm not a farmer, שבע שני הוי כפנא, Sheva shani
havei kafna, there could be, you know, it's apparently like a common
saying, there could be a famine for seven years, דבבא אומנא לא
חליף, debava umna lo chalif, but by the door of a craftsman,
it has no impact. You know, so what? So there's no rain.
I'm a doctor, I'm a lawyer, I'll make, you know, it doesn't
influence my business. So אלא אמר רבא, ela Amar Rava, so rather
רבא Rava says, אמרינן להו, amrinan lehu, we say the following: מפיץ
וחרב וחץ שנון איש עונה ברעהו עד שקר. mafitz vecherev vechetz shanun
ish onneh vere'ehu ed shaker. So like, you know, a sword and
a sharpened arrow is a person who testifies falsely against his friend,
which again is being read not just as a metaphor but saying
as a result of this there's going to be war. Okay. So
אמר רב אשי, Amar Rav Ashi, יכיל למימר, yachil lemeimar, or you
know, there's going to be death. יכיל למימר, yachil lemeimar, he could
still say שבע שני הוי מותנא, Sheva shani havei motna,
so what, there's a saying
there could be, you know, there could be a death for seven
years, pestilence or whatever, ואנש בלא שני לא שכיב, vinash belo shnei
lo shachiv, and nobody dies when it's not their time. So they'll
have a pretty hard time with him. All right, that might be
true, but so what, there'll be war, nobody passes away before their
time. אלא אמר רב אשי, ela Amar Rav Ashi, I'm not worried
about that. אמר ליה נתן בר מר זוטרא, Amar leh Natan bar
Mar Zutra, אמרינן להו, amrinan lehu, this is what we say to
them: סהדי שקרי אוגרייהו זילי. Sahadei shikrei ogreihu zilei. False witnesses, even
for those that have hired them, are despicable. Okay, you know, you'll
think you'll get your money and people, you know, the people will
be so grateful, but even the people who hire you treat you
with disgust. Okay, despise you. דכתיב, Dechsiv, והושיבו שנים אנשים בני בליעל
נגדו. vehoshibu shnayim anashim bnei beliya'al negdo. This is by the case
of the, what was it, the כרם של נבות, kerem shel Navot,
right, the vineyard of Navot, that the king was trying to falsely
take away from him and hired these false witnesses and they had
two people sit against him, people of בליעל, beliya'al, people of like
disrepute, okay, ויעידהו לאמר ברכת אלהים ומלך, vaye'iduhu lemor berachta Elohim vamelech,
and they testified against him that he had blasphemed God and the
king, but the point is even the king who was hiring these
witnesses treated them as people of, you know, of ill repute. Okay,
בליעל beliya'al is even a harsher word than ill repute, corrupt, I
guess, right, exactly. So you know what they're basically saying to you,
you know, you are going to be despised even by the people
that hired you. So, all right, that's much more personal. Okay, אם
אמר הוא אמר לי וכולי, Im amar hu amar li vechulei, עד
שיאמר בפנינו הודה לו שהוא חייב לו מאתים זוז. ad sheyomar befanenu
hodeh lo shehu chayav lo matayim zuz. If it's not enough to
say he said it to me, you have to say I was
there when he admitted to the other guy. מסייעא ליה לרב יהודה,
Mesaye'a leh leRav Yehuda, this supports רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, דאמר רב
יהודה אמר רב, d'amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, צריך שיאמר אתם עדי.
tzarich sheyomar atem eday. Now this is taking it one step further.
Here, if I admit to Michael, Michael says, you know, you owe
me $100 and I say yes, I do owe you $100 and
there's ראובן ושמעון Reuven veShimon who were there, now from our משנה
you would think, okay, I directly admitted it to Michael. רב יהודה
אמר רב Rav Yehuda amar Rav goes one step further and he
says, who was it, רב יהודה אמר רב, Rav Yehuda amar Rav,
no, רב יהודה. Rav Yehuda. רב יהודה Rav Yehuda says it's not
enough that I said to Michael yes I owe you, I have
to turn to ראובן ושמעון Reuven veShimon and say, ראובן ושמעון, Reuven
veShimon, you be my witnesses that I'm admitting to Michael that I
owe him $100. That's certainly taking that's going to really limit cases
where you can bring, you know, find a guy, you know, liable
for an admission. Okay, he has to directly identify or maybe Michael
can identify the witnesses. I say yes I owe you $100 and
Michael says to ראובן ושמעון, Reuven veShimon, can they be your witnesses
against that, and I would have, you know, or they will be
your witnesses, but without designating them, that's not an admission. Is that
even in the case where you see them do the transaction? No,
not where you see them do the transaction. This is about admission.
How much is an admission taken as a serious legal, legally binding
admission? Okay, so איתמר נמי, itmar nami, it was also said, אמר
רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן, amar Rabbi Chiyya bar Abba
amar Rabbi Yochanan, we'll just skip the bracket, or whatever I guess
we'll read it, מנה לי בידך אמר לו הן, maneh li beyadecha
amar lo hen, למחר אמר לו תניהו לי, lemachar amar lo tenehu
li, אמר משטה אני בך. amar meshateh ani becha. And here's the,
oh I was just kidding, yeah, even though there were witnesses when
I said yes, I was just saying it to get you off
my back because you've been, you know, nudging me so long. So
it doesn't matter that there were witnesses, I wasn't seriously admitting to
it. פטור, Patur, you're exempt. תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, מנה
לי בידך אמר לו הן, maneh li beyadecha amar lo hen, למחר
אמר לו תניהו לי, lemachar amar lo tenehu li, אמר לו משטה
אני בך. amar lo meshateh ani becha. I was just kidding around
with you. פטור, Patur, you're exempt. And even though witnesses testified to
that. ולא עוד אלא אפילו הכמין לו עדים אחורי הגדר. Velo od
ela afillu hichmin lo edim achorei hageder. So Michael knows that I've
been trying to get out with it, so he... as he was
hidden and hiding behind the wall. ואמר לו Ve-amar lo and Michael
says: מנה לי בידך? maneh li beyadecha? אמר לו הין, Amar lo
hein, yes. Then Michael goes further, he says: רצונך שתודה בפני פלוני
ופלוני? Retzoncha she-todeh bifnei ploni u-ploni? and let's say Michael says: Are
you prepared to admit that before witnesses? אמר לו Amar lo and
I say to them: מתיירא אני שמא תכפיני לדין. Mityarei ani shema
tichpinei le-din. No, I'm not going to admit in front of witnesses
because then you'll be able to bring me in and make me
actually have to pay you. Okay, which makes it sound very clear
that I'm admitting that I owe and I'm just trying to get
out of actually having to be found responsible, you know, found liable.
So למחר אמר לו תנה לי, L'machar amar lo tneh li, where's
the hundred dollars you owe me? אמר לו משטה אני בך, Amar
lo meshateh ani bach, I was kidding. פטור, Patur, he's exempt, even
though Michael produces the witnesses who heard me say that I'm not
going to admit it in front of witnesses because I don't want
to have to be forced to pay. Okay. ואין טוענין למסית. Ve-ein
to'anin le-mesit. And by the way, you also don't come and argue
on behalf of a person who is a who seduces somebody to
sin. So what?
מסית מן דכר שמיה? Mesit man d'char shemeih? Since when were we
talking about a מסית?
mesit? So the גמרא says חסורי מחסרא והכי קתני. Chassurei mechassra ve-hachi
katni. No, no, it's missing some words. Here's how you have to
read it. אם לא טען אין טוענין לו. Im lo ta'an ein
to'anin lo. Now, if Michael comes and says where's the hundred dollars
you owe me and I say what are you talking about and
Michael produces the witnesses that he hid behind the גדר geder who
heard me admit that I owe the hundred dollars, okay, if I
say I was just kidding, then I'm believed. But if I don't
say I was just kidding, the בית דין doesn't turn to me
and say: Is it possible you were just kidding when you said
to Michael? They don't suggest that, okay. If there's witnesses that heard
me admit it to Michael, I would be believed to claim I
wasn't serious, but until I say that we're going to assume that
it actually was a real admission. אין טוענין לו. Ein to'anin lo.
ובדיני נפשות, U-ve-dinei nefashot, but in those cases too, right? Not just...
Right, it's all the other cases too. There might be some cases
where there was like the תוספות Tosafot asks the question. Let's say
I go and I'm just getting out the ice cream with David
and as we're talking I'm saying: Yeah, I owe Michael a hundred
dollars. So I didn't even admit it to you, I was just
talking to him. That might be a case where I don't have
to be saying I was just kidding, that's not even in a
context of a serious admission all together. But when I'm admitting to
you and you then produce witnesses and I didn't say אתם עדי
atem edai or they were hiding or whatever the case was, that
would be a case where if I don't say I was kidding,
we treat it as serious. Okay. ובדיני נפשות, U-ve-dinei nefashot, but in
a capital crime אף על גב דלא טען טוענין לו. af al
gav d'lo ta'an to'anin lo. If somebody has a way that they
can make a claim that they didn't actually, you know, do the
crime or they weren't actually, you know, intentional or whatever the case
might be, we will argue it on that person's behalf even if
they themselves don't claim it because it's our responsibility to try to
save somebody from being executed. Okay. ואין טוענין למסית. Ve-ein to'anin le-mesit.
The one person who we don't argue on their behalf is the
person who seduces people to idolatry. Okay, that's a category where actually
where if the person if he were to make a claim maybe
he would get off the hook, but we're not interested in trying
to explore that possibility if they don't raise it. Okay, now מאי
שנא מסית? mai shna mesit? Why is מסית mesit so worse than
anything else? I mean, why is it worse than murder? Murder we'll
try to come up with an argument to defend the person, but
not for a מסית. mesit. So אמר רבי חמא בר חנינא מפרקי
דבי רבי חייא בר אבא שמיע לי, Amar Rabbi Chama bar Chanina
mi-pirkei d'vei Rabbi Chiyya bar Abba shemi'a li, I heard this from
the teaching of רבי חייא בר אבא. Rabbi Chiyya bar Abba. שאני
מסית דרחמנא אמר, Shani mesit de-Rachmana amar, מסית mesit is different, the
רחמנא Rachmana says לא תחמל ולא תכסה עליו. lo tachmol ve-lo techaseh
alav. Don't have compassion and don't try to protect him. Now, of
course, תכסה techaseh means to protect when you know that he's guilty.
Cover up.
Cover up, exactly.
But here it's being read as don't do anything to argue on
this person's behalf. Presumably because this is a person, you know, it's
not just an individual crime, they're influencing a wide range of people
and they're subverting God's authority, right? The מסית mesit for עבודה זרה.
Avodah Zarah. So this type of thing is so much that you
really want to take extra precautions to protect the community and you're
not- you know, that's always the question, right? About
do you, you know, what was the Greek line? Better what is
it like a hundred murderers should go free rather than to imprison
one, you know, one innocent man? Right, but you know, but that's
always the question, balancing the interest of society against
protecting the individual. So the מסית mesit is seen as such a
grave threat to God and to, you know, to God's authority and
to society and so on that we do not try to argue
on his behalf. I thought there was like if you lead the
community to sin then there's no תשובה. teshuvah. Right, but that's תשובה,
teshuvah, right, yeah, exactly, but it's a similar point. Right. ואמר שמואל
בר נחמני אמר רבי יונתן: Ve-amar Shmuel bar Nachmani amar Rabbi Yonatan:
מנין שאין טוענין למסית? Minayin she-ein to'anin le-mesit? Where do you know
this? מנחש הקדמוני, mi-nachash hakadmoni, from the first serpent. Okay. דאמר רבי
שמלאי: De-amar Rabbi Simlai: הרבה טענות היה לו לנחש לטעון. Harbeh ta'anot
hayah lo la-nachash lit'on. That נחש nachash when God said to him
what did you do, you know, you caused חוה ואדם Chava ve-Adam
to sin, he could have made a lot of claims in his
defense. ולא טען, Ve-lo ta'an, and he didn't say them. ומפני מה
לא טען לו הקדוש ברוך הוא? U-mipnei mah lo ta'an lo ha-Kadosh
Baruch Hu? So why the נחש nachash didn't say them isn't our
interest, but why did God not argue on his defense? לפי שלא
טען הוא, Lefi she-lo ta'an hu, because he didn't argue for himself.
And therefore and therefore God לא טען לו. lo ta'an lo. לא
טענינן למסית, Lo ta’aninan lemasit, okay? Now and this again was a
similar מסית. masit. It was you could just say it's a מסית
masit to any sin, but the bigger point being is like he's
a מסית masit to you know which undermined God's authority. The מסית
masit in the תורה'ס Torah's to עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. And this
is a מסית, masit, you know, it's all about the one thing
God said, right? The whole point of the sin was not the
sin itself of eating from the tree, it was that that represented
are you going to subject yourself to God's authority or not subject
yourself to God's authority, right? So therefore God was so so God
did not come to his defense. Now מה הוה ליה למימר? Ma
hava lei lemeimar? What could he have said? דברי הרב ודברי התלמיד
דברי מי שומעין? Divrei HaRav vedivrei hatalmid divrei mi shom'in? Because fine,
that every מסית masit could say that. So the master says one
thing, the student says another thing, who do you listen to? So
fine, I said not to disobey, you're going to listen to me?
You should listen to God. Every מסית masit can make that claim.
It's interesting it says he could have said a lot of things.
We're only giving one thing he could have said. Anyway let's just
end this. דברי מי שומעין, Divrei mi shom'in, דברי הרב שומעין. Divrei
HaRav shom'in. Okay. אמר חזקיה, Amar Chizkiyah, מניין שכל המוסיף גורע? Minayin
shekol hamosif goreia? How do you know that whoever adds takes away?
שנאמר, Shene'emar, אמר אלוהים לא תאכלו ממנו ולא תגעו בו, Amar Elokim
lo tochlu mimenu velo tigu bo, right? It's because אדם Adam said
to, you know, חוה Chava said to the נחש, Nachash, God says
don't eat and don't touch. God only said don't eat. And this
is the famous מדרש Midrash that once חוה Chava said that God
said don't touch, the נחש Nachash pushed her against the tree and
said ah, you see, you could touch it and nothing will happen,
the same will be if you eat from it. So you see
כל המוסיף גורע. Kol hamosif goreia. Now I have to stop and
tell you that there is an אבות דרבי נתן Avot D'Rabbi Natan
that is very, very subversive because one of the first teachings in
פרקי אבות Pirkei Avot is, you know, that they said הם אמרו
שלושה דברים, Hem amru shlosha devarim, which the אנשי כנסת הגדולה, Anshei
Knesset HaGedolah, העמידו תלמידים הרבה, He'amidu talmidim harbeh, והוו מתונים בדין, Vahavu
metunim badin, ועשו סייג לתורה. Ve'asu siyag laTorah. So the גמרא says,
so the אבות דרבי נתן Avot D'Rabbi Natan says, הקדוש ברוך הוא
עשה סייג לדבריו, HaKadosh Baruch Hu asa siyag lidvarav, משה עשה סייג
לדבריו, Moshe asa siyag lidvarav, אדם הראשון עשה סייג לדבריו. Adam HaRishon
asa siyag lidvarav. So what was the סייג siyag that אדם הראשון
Adam HaRishon did לדבריו? lidvarav? So God said don't eat and אדם
Adam when he told חוה Chava said don't eat and don't touch.
And then he said and then the נחש Nachash he touched her,
whatever, and and the whole sin happened. So it's like so why
is that a subversive point? Right? It's like you're supposed to make
a fence, but how do you balance the idea of making a
fence with בל תוסיף Bal tosif and כל המוסיף גורע, Kol hamosif
goreia, right? That sometimes adding takes away. So this like אבות דרבי
נתן Avot D'Rabbi Natan just like puts the two together and it's
like leaves you to figure that out. But anyway here's כל המוסיף
גורע, Kol hamosif goreia, but it could also be used as you
know are you supposed to be עושה סייג לדבריו? Oseh siyag lidvarav?
Anyway so let's just finish this. What do you do about that?
Ah that's a different שיעור. shiur. רב משארשיא אמר מהכא: Rav Mesharshiya
amar meihacha: אמתים וחצי ארכו. Amatayim vachatzi arko. So how's that כל
המוסיף גורע? Kol hamosif goreia? Because if you added the אלף, aleph,
what would it have been if you took out the אלף? aleph?
What would it have said? מתיים וחצי, Matayim vachatzi, two hundred. אמתים
וחצי Amatayim vachatzi means two אמות. amot. So the adding of the
אלף aleph made the word, wait a second, you'd have to still
need an אלף, aleph, it would just be between the מם... mem...
רש"י Rashi says מתיים matayim we didn't need an אלף aleph for
the pronunciation. Anyway רב אשי אמר עשתי עשרה יריעות, Rav Ashi amar
ashtei esrei yeriot, eleven יריעות. yeriot. So if you take away the
עין, ayin, it's שתי עשרה, shtei esrei, twelve. Oh yeah, the עין,
ayin, it's eleven. Okay. And let's just turn the page. אמר אביי
לא שנו אלא דאמר משטה אני בך, Amar Abaye lo shanu ela
de'amar mishteh ani bach, that now as we said he has to
claim I was kidding. So it's only if he says he was
kidding. אבל אמר לא היו דברים מעולם, Aval amar lo hayu devarim
me'olam, if he says I never said such a thing and then
you bring witnesses that he said it, הוחזק כפרן, Huchzak kafran, he's
a proven liar. Okay, so it's if he did not say אתם
עדי, Atem edai, he's believed to say I was kidding. But he's
not believed to say it never happened. And if he says it
never happened, then his whole then his whole, you know, his whole
like it undermines his whole, you know, his whole authority to claim
things. רש"י says you wouldn't believe him let's say to make a
שבועה shvuah after that. רב פפא Rav Papa disagrees. רב פפא בריה
דרב אחא בר אדא הכי אמר משמיה דרבא: Rav Papa breih deRav
Acha bar Adda hachi amar mishmeih deRava: כל מידי דכדי לא דכיר
אינש. Kol midei dechadi lo dachir inash. Things that are meaningless, people
don't remember. So if in the same way he can claim I
was kidding since you know he could also say like he say
I never said such a thing and then Michael brings witnesses that
I did say it, it's who remembers? I wasn't serious. I did
say it but I wasn't remembering. So I'm not a proven liar
from the same token that I could say I was kidding. If
I said it never happened and it did happen, I'm not a
proven liar because it could be I just didn't remember. Okay, so
we will stop here for today.